software engineering radio episode 90
product line engineering part 3 with
Charles kugel
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the hot
rod
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to software
engineering radio before we get to the
actual content of this episode I do have
a couple of announcements just wanted to
quickly mention that as your radio now
has a web shop a cafe press shop local
talk I'll set it up for us
you can buy their coffee mugs t-shirts
and you know the usual stuff so if you
want to make sure as your radio gets
more well-known its promoted to go there
buy this stuff and well walk around to
the logo thanks just some quick reminder
that you should go to su Radio dotnet
and click on the well on the link on the
left side the get together link they get
together is the open space conference
you're organizing together with tape on
EDX the German team magazine go to the
website look at the last PDF you put
together with all details and well we
would like to see you there it's
important for radio to be mentioned on
sites like Reddit dick delicious or
slash dot we have put those special
shortcut links into each episode page so
you just have to click there so you
would really do as a great favor if
you'd make su radio more well-known by
mentioning those certain episodes on
those pages and also voting them up
because most of these pages obviously
work by social bookmarking or other web
2.0 facilities so people have to vote
for the content so if one person just
submits it and then nothing else happens
it's not very useful so please help us
make this stuff more well-known both
these things up and if you like them of
course we don't ask you to vote for crap
and you should only vote for the good
episodes the ones you like best okay and
here is the actual episode my name is
Michael and my guest today is Charles
Kruger Charles Kruger is a bank member
of the software product lines community
and Charles why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners okay thank you
Michael so I am currently the CEO of big
leaver software founder of that company
as well we focus entirely on
for product line development technology
and methodologies we've been doing that
work for about six years now and focused
on commercial practice and commercial
deployments okay and your own background
in software product lines is that the
same as the the company existed or what
is your personal history was product
line engineering so it all started back
in the late 80s early 90s in my graduate
research so I was very interested in
software reuse and the technologies
around that and my PhD thesis work at
Carnegie Mellon was in what today might
be called product line architectures
back then it didn't have that name but
it was reusable and configurable
software architectures and that's
ultimately where my interest started
after I got out of graduate school
worked in a couple of commercial
companies applied some of the ideas and
a couple of them worked better than you
might expect and eventually those good
ideas that were working well in practice
were what turned into the company you
mentioned the term broad outline
architecture I always wondered what is
really a product line architecture I
like much more to term reference
architecture do you distinguish those
two what do you think about this term
product line architecture and what what
does it mean to you so product line
architecture certainly the idea of being
focused in a specific product domain
application domain is the idea there
reference architecture is a probably a
term that's been used longer sometimes
that reference architecture can be more
of a generic architecture that might be
used across many application domains
whereas product line architectures tend
to be narrowly focused on a very
specific portfolio of products within a
single domain but a similar intent for
sure and what does the broad outline
architecture what is it different from a
regular
through the product line architecture
will look identical to a regular
architecture except for the notion of
variation or diversity so what you want
to accommodate in your product line
architecture is the ability to say you
know here's an architect a part of the
architecture that will vary among
different products within a portfolio
and the ability to have optional
structures within your architecture or
structures that may come in different
flavors depending on the product that
you're building
I guess this can be pretty difficult I
mean if you imagine that you have really
different really are very different
products that you derive from the
product line architecture and you need
to document all the variabilities and
all the options are there any best
practices have you seen them around an
industry usually what happens is if you
find the diversity is becoming too much
there's too much variation what you may
find is that you actually have two
product lines or multiple product lines
and and a lot of times what you'll want
to do is go to a what's referred to as a
product population where you have
multiple families living together if you
will but you have then would go to
multiple product line architectures that
may have more similarity internally
within them and then have a family of
those architectures that are a
population of those architectures that
ultimately have some sharing as well but
if the commonality if the common parts
of that architecture are not high enough
then you're not going to gain the
benefits of the reuse and and that
commonality ultimately that's the the
goal is to benefit from what's common
and have very manageable levels of
variability within there is there any
rule of thumb about the commonality that
you
to have so that the product line
architectural product line of roads
actually made makes sense what we find
and this is maybe more towards the
implementation level but if you look at
how many common files or common modules
versus how much what percentage of the
files or modules within a system may
vary we usually find that 75 80 percent
is a pretty typical number so if you
have less than that you know if I see
somebody that's got less than 50 percent
commonality within architecture or
within a set of implementation assets
then I start to worry a little bit that
the reuse levels are not high enough and
there may be some issues so we look for
ways of maybe refactoring or repartition
inor dividing into multiple product
lines to get those numbers closer to 75
or 80 or 90% an interesting and
challenging question that I raised
already several times in the past was
well what is in your opinion the key
difference between software product line
engineering and regular software
engineering is product line engineering
just software engineering done right
what is different how how would you
differentiate the two terms practices
okay
definitely a good question the way we
like to look at it is you do your
product line engineering in exactly the
way you would manage the entire
lifecycle of doing development software
engineering on a single system but at
every stage within that lifecycle you
now need to consider the concept of
variability and diversity and so if you
start at requirements then go through
your architecture design implementation
test cases documentation deployment
whatever your lifecycle may be for your
software assets and your software
development if at every stage in the
lifecycle you can accommodate the
variability and relate the variability
among the different stages in the
same way that you would do your
traceability for conventional software
development then it all of a sudden
becomes very similar to developing
software in a very traditional
conventional way so the you know again
it's all about managing very effectively
managing that variability at every stage
in the lifecycle so it's the consequence
that we don't need any additional
technologies and processes to accomplish
succeeding and product line engineering
or do we need them what is like your
your reasoning here so the reason that
our company exists we have a tool called
gears that provides the variability
management in software assets in the
early stages of trying these ideas and
in my thesis and the first commercial
deployments we tried to use conventional
technologies such as configuration
management branching or conditionals
through if deaths or runtime conviction
conditionals and configuration files it
turns out that conventional technology
trying to then mix in the variability
management with these conventional
software management techniques creates a
lot of complexity so ultimately what we
found is there's a hole in our existing
toolset and methodology and software
development and so you know the reason
the company exists is we created a tool
to fill that gap so you've you have you
many customers all over the world and
what is what is the state of Industry
regarding product line engineering what
is common practice today out there the
idea of creating a portfolio of products
is not new by any means and it's not a
concept that comes out of the
engineering department the business
groups the the marketing the sales group
all want to have diversity and
variations within a product line in
order to sell more into more markets and
to ultimately make more money
so the engineering groups in response
have applied conventional techniques to
the best of their ability into the best
practices but ultimately that's not
sufficient so the companies that are
doing the best you know take a first
class method and first class technology
for dealing with product line approach
but most of the companies would go into
our again using things like the if
deaths or configuration management
branches not that there's anything wrong
with that those are what we have in our
toolbox today and that's what people use
and they use those things very well but
they scale well to you know maybe 10 15
or 20 products within a portfolio then
the complexity starts to ramp up pretty
steeply and so that's what we find state
of the practice
everybody's doing portfolios of products
companies typically are feeling a lot of
pain and spending a lot of time and
energy on the overhead of managing the
engineering of a portfolio in that
diversity so and a new approach is to
solve this complexity and succeed in in
product line engineering with a
technology and and tool approach what
about organizational issues what about
management issue is what about process
issues what do you have any impact there
do you do do you have any suggestions on
those areas so we've have what we call a
three tiered software product line
methodology that provides a simple
framework for describing methods
processes tools techniques and a way of
capturing best practices that you know
provides that level of guidance we're
learning you know as we go this is still
an emerging field I would say and so we
have customers having very good success
and every time we go in and look at
at what's working well or where they're
having challenges in deploying their
product lines will capture that in the
methodology but so the three TR broads
who contains some management guidance
here and process guidance suggestions
and on how to deal with that yes so the
the first tier of the methodology
primarily focuses on infrastructure
technology how to integrate variability
management in with configuration
management and build and those types of
technical techniques the second tier in
the methodology is really where we start
to look at the organizational and
process issues top tier then is more
business focused and how do you get your
business and your engineering
organization working very efficiently
together yeah best practices on those
areas you name one well so let's look at
the the middle tier for example so once
you do have a very good technology base
in place for managing your diversity
then we go into what's called a core
asset focused development so the
traditional way of managing product
portfolio deployments is you have a team
of people that's focused on the release
schedule and getting products out the
door at a particular time and so the
organization is all around the lifecycle
of individual products you'll tend to
have teams clustered around products
what we do is sort of flip that 90
degrees and say what you really want to
do is have all of your organizational
structures focused around the reusable
subsystems what are referred to as the
core assets and have no development
teams focused on the individual products
the actual deployment of the products is
managed through automatic configuration
of products from core assets so then you
if I understand that correctly you
totally focus on the core assets
you have some some derivation rules that
you star in your tool and you then
derive the products from it so what what
stays after this derivation when you
delivered it to the customer how do you
know what actually you deliver to the
customer do you keep a configuration
file or something around in
configuration management what what is
the asset that you keep of a specific
product then yes so in the traditional
way of doing a single product what you
would do is have a for example a
configuration management label or a
baseline that you would remember and
that way you can go back and reproduce
that product every file every byte
within every file is 100% reproducible
when you have core assets from which
you're deriving products now you need an
additional step you know you take your
baseline of your core assets that still
have the diversity in them then you
provide a specification what we call a
feature profile that says here's the
optional features we want in here's the
ones we don't want those features that
come in different flavors here's the
particular flavor of that feature we're
interested in and if you take a feature
profile apply it to a baseline of core
assets from configuration management
that takes you right back to the same
scenario where you can reproduce every
byte of every file that gets deployed to
a customer so you get that 100%
reproducibility again the listeners
might remember our first episode on
product line engineering and in this
first episode Marcus and I had a
discussion about problem and solution
space and how to how to make the hop
from the problem space from the
requirements to the to the solutions how
to do the traceability Charles what is
what is your advice on how to tie the
requirements the variability in the
requirements with the variable
and in the solution how do you trace
these requirements than Indus motion so
if you have well-defined variation what
we call variation points within your
requirements so you identify and
encapsulate here's a requirement that
comes in different ways for different
products and then have those variation
points that exist all the way through
the entire lifecycle you can add your
traceability in the same way that you
would in conventional software so a
variation point within your requirements
will trace to one or more variation
points within your architecture which
points within your implementation so
you'll have a many-to-many relationship
at each between each stage in your life
cycle and in the same way that you do
your traceability among the common parts
of your requirements and architectures
and designs and implementations same way
within the diversity and you can use the
identical sets of techniques so what you
need then is this first-class notion of
variation point at every stage in the
lifecycle I'm very used to to feature
models as they are for example provided
by Christoph Czarnecki in his tooling
what is your approach different or is it
is it the same like feature models would
what are the fundamental ideas of your
approach compared to feature monly
so we follow the same paradigm there
will be a feature model we use that term
feature model for managing at that level
of abstraction
what is the diversity that exists within
the portfolio so one of the things
that's slightly different with our
approach is that we model only feature
diversity and don't use the feature
model to necessarily model all features
that are both common and varying so
we're getting it down to the essence of
making choices among a feature set that
will help uniquely characterize each
product
our language for describing feature
models is slightly different we don't
follow the photo language directly we
use something that we find is more
comfortable and familiar for developers
so we use things like set types and
enumeration types and primitive types
such as integer strings characters
boolean z' so things that make it very
easy for a developer to move from
conventional development into software
product line development and then what I
always do is go back and make sure that
we're at least isomorphic with what
Christoph is doing I kind of use his
work as a good standard we want to make
sure we can represent everything that
can be represented in photo or you know
Christoph's approaches for feature
modeling and we tend to go beyond that
as well and be able to represent more
complex features and particularly the
feature constraints and interactions is
there any integration of those two
approaches that people have already a
feature model of their domain how could
they reuse it for example with the
tooling that you suggest there is so if
you look at you know the various
characterizations in a feature model
tree or feature model diagram you can
pretty much look at every one of those
levels and say oh this needs to be
converted into a set or this needs to be
converted to an enumeration ultimately
what we're doing right now we're doing
some work with Honeywell to produce a
graphical representation of our language
that will look very much like a
traditional photo diagram there are some
people in their product marketing group
there that prefer the diagrammatic
graphical approach if they're not
programmer so they prefer to interact
with the visual representations so
ultimately there will be a way to look
at those two things side by side and
they're going to look very similar okay
including the hierarchy
because as I understand in the future
models with the future tree are
typically hierarchies of variabilities
of variation points and and your
language supports as I understand it a
flat structure of variation points now
it will be well so the feature model in
our world is definitely hierarchical so
you can have a set type and then a
member of that set could be a nested set
or it could be a nested enumeration so
anything that has multiple children can
be nested ultimately the leaves of that
tree are the primitive types within the
language so you do have a tree structure
there our notion of variation point to
sort of put a little differentiation in
here feature model for us is all about
again managing feature diversity so
pretty much every feature in our feature
model will be varying will represent
diversity and then our what we refer to
as a variation point is at the
implementation level so we really don't
talk about variation points within the
feature model we sort of assume all of
that is varying and representing
diversity a variation point is at the
next level below of abstraction where
your modeling variation within some
asset ok is there any better source
available that the listeners could look
up and and follow your thoughts and
ideas on this topic we have definitely a
lot of resources on our website so
there's a sort of a learn more section
there so you can see online demos we do
live web seminars quite frequently many
papers we've written on specific topics
white papers case studies so we're very
informational in the way that we do our
marketing within the company it's all
about doing information particularly
have a newsletter that goes out about
once a month and that's just the
lightest and absolute you know
recent evolving experiences concepts
case studies that are coming out so
that's a great way to really keep up
with the leading edge of what we're
learning and finding out we put the link
into the show notes
another topic well that's what I find
one of one of the hardest topics is how
to get started I mean many developers
and many managers feel the need for for
a structured and systematic approach to
product line engineering but then the
hard part is how to get started how to
get your organization convinced how do
you get your upper management convinced
how do you get the people convinced that
are involved in configuration management
in the tooling in the architecture and
everything how do you start something
like that definitely it's a challenge
because it's an emerging discipline is
one of the challenges people are not
familiar with it they haven't heard with
it heard of it you know or don't have
experience with it
it looks like risk and people tend to be
averse to that so you have to at least
find one person within the organization
who enjoys doing new things new
challenges who tends to be bored with
the way things are done and very
dissatisfied with the complexity of
conventional approaches so you need a
good individual that's going to champion
the cause we've really I think pioneered
a lot of what we call the minimally
invasive conversion techniques
transition techniques so we look at how
can you start with whatever you're doing
today legacy assets legacy approaches
and make very small incremental steps
that don't require a lot of change a lot
of time a lot of money or effort so that
you can do something next week that will
make you better off the following week
and we found some very good techniques
for that so our customers may invest you
know set
side - engineers for two months to start
a transition process at the end of those
two months they'll actually have a
functioning product line infrastructure
in place addressing a very limited
amount of the core assets or the
existing legacy code but once you take
that first incremental step you're a
little bit better off you can use your
gains in productivity or whatever then
reinvest that into incrementally
transitioning the next step and we find
that to be a very effective approach so
then it becomes less intimidating you
don't have to convince management to
take these huge leaps of faith while
you're investing you know hundreds of
man-hours and man months of effort to
try to make a transition on what parts
of the system do you focus and what kind
of assets under requirements first or do
you try to get some solution artifacts
managed properly we we go for where the
pain is the worst where's the biggest
problem where's the biggest opportunity
for gains a lot of times that's in the
source code right that's where you've
got the most largest number of Engineers
largest number of burn right man-hours
going on every week every month
so typically we'll focus on let's take
one subsystem and convert that into core
assets or let's take two products out of
your portfolio and consolidate two
products so that they work like a
product line and then incrementally
transition in other products so we find
ways of saying let's start with a small
number of people either focus on one
subsystem or focus on small numbers of
products and make the transition at that
level so it really you know it depends
but a lot of times we see people making
transitions either around here's one
subsystem we think we can tackle without
a lot of disruption or here's a pair of
products that we can start with they're
at the end of a release cycle you know
maybe another quart
six months before they release again so
let's start working on those any
indicators is another key term and key
topic for me what are some of the most
common pain indicators that that people
feel the situations when you actually
have a chance to convince them to use a
product line engineering approach and
instead of a tradition or not so
systematic approach what are those pain
indicators the things we see will be as
you start adding more and more products
to the portfolio it becomes more
extremely more expensive and more
difficult every time you add a new
product so you've sort of get to a point
on an exponential curve where you almost
hit the wall you know you can add your
sixteenth product but you can never get
to seventeen because you're so busy
thrashing around on those first 16 so it
shows up in the form of defects so an
engineer will go in fix the defect on
one product and oops I accidentally
broke two others as I was doing that
because that entanglement of that of the
diversity we see things where maybe a
company is using a branching technique
in configuration management and they'll
notice that engineers are spending all
of their time merging across branches
within configuration management so it's
it's sort of wasted overhead people
doing things that don't relate to adding
value and adding features to the product
they're just thrashing around trying to
manage diversity and variation and just
keeping things coordinated now what kind
of domains are best suited for a product
line engineering approach are the
domains like telecommunication embedded
systems banking or - like that that are
have been typically and in the past very
intense
usage of product lines this product line
engineering suited for any kind of
domain so we haven't seen any limitation
in terms of where you can apply the
concept so it's very broad very
horizontal type of concept that applies
in all software areas in terms of
adoption we do find that embedded types
of development seem to be more amenable
to trying and adopting software product
line approaches and I attribute that to
the fact that the notion of product line
is so clear when you're working in a
domain that has physical devices so that
you know you get a twenty handsets for a
cell phone dropped on your desk and and
somebody says write software that runs
on all twenty of these different
handsets it's very clear you have a
product line problem whereas in
enterprise software there are 50
different ways that people will come up
with of managing the variability in that
diversity and they don't as clearly see
the fact that they do have a product
line problem now you have to change that
many people many developers many
software engineers currently listen to
you do you have anything that you want
to across to to this group of people
that you always liked to say well the
certainly we're at a point now in the
field where product lines are well
understood they're proven in practice
I've never seen a case where you go in
and do a study and say oh you'd be
better off not adopting a product line
approach so I think it's to the point
now where it will be headed into the
mainstream we're seeing more and more
people understanding it and there's
really no reason not to to go after it
the benefits are always there it's very
exciting very challenging but always
very strong benefits come in response to
that so I just encourage people to look
very closely at
what's available out in the the
methodologies and the technologies that
are emerging look at those success
stories and and find good ways of being
one of the first people out there to
have another success story there is
going to happen the software product
lines conference this fall in Japan what
can people learn from that at that
conference
what is it says how people get into the
product lines community how to get
started how to become potentially a
member of the product line engineering
community so the first five years or so
of the software product line conference
it was all researchers and people coming
in and and everybody there had their
view of how to do product lines
everybody was speaking nobody was
listening kind of scenario very
interesting we learned a lot but over
the last three or four years the
conference is now becoming dominated by
practitioners and so you'll go there and
the hallways are full of practitioners
who are there may be experienced or may
be brand new but you know everybody's
there away from work away from email
away from the phone calls living
breathing eating drinking software
product lines very a way to get deeply
immersed talk to the people who are
really making it happen
and it's a great scenario so I'll see
companies who come there for the first
time and then a year later you'll talk
to them at the next one and they'll be
doing product line practice and having
success so in terms of deep immersion
and really jump-starting a initiative
into doing software product lines it's a
great approach great any final word any
last words you want to say to our
listeners well I just appreciate the
opportunity to get out here and spread
the word that's our mission ultimately
is to get this out into the mainstream
again you know information is out there
dig in be one of the early adopters and
I think the field now is is at a point
where we're seeing a very rapid growth
very rapid adoption and nothing but good
things to come all right
find your chance thank you very much
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and su radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie Crowell
and the pot safe music Network for the
music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]